Guide to the Elias Perkins Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Elias Perkins papers
1784-1833
MS 1013
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
Correspondence and miscellaneous documents reflecting Elias Perkins attendance at Yale College (1782-1786) and his political activities as a member of the 7th Congress of the U.S. and as judge of the New London County Court. Also included are papers of Nathaniel Shaw Perkins documenting his Yale career (1808-1812), his service in the War of 1812, and his admission to the University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine. The papers also include a letter on Nathaniel Shaw from the U.S. State Department (1900).
Perkins, Elias, 1767-1845
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Separated from the Nathaniel and Thomas Shaw Papers, 1951 and 1980.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains certificates and other papers of Elias Perkins and his son Nathaniel Shaw Perkins. The papers of Elias Perkins consist of several letters, notices, and certificates recording his election to Phi Beta Kappa, his election to Congress, his appointment to the public examination committee for Yale College, his appointment as judge of the New London, Connecticut, County Court, and votes of thanks from Yale officials, as well as his Yale B.A. diploma. There are also two orations by Perkins and a copy of the Freshman Laws, possibly in his hand.
The papers of Nathaniel Shaw Perkins (1797-1870) consist of a receipt for his Yale College tuition, his B.A. and M.A. diplomas, certificates of appointment as a military surgeon, receipts and cards of admission to classes at the University of Pennsylvania Medical School, and a certificate of appointment as a royal arch mason.
The final item in the collection is a letter from the United States State Department to Nathaniel Shaw Perkins (1822-1905) concerning Nathaniel Shaw.
These papers were separated in 1951 and 1980 from the Nathaniel and Thomas Shaw Papers (Ms. Gr. No. 445). The latter collection was given to Yale University as a memorial to Nathaniel Shaw Perkins by his daughter, Jane R. Perkins, and her brothers in 1926.
Biographical / Historical
Elias Perkins was born in Newent Society, now Lisbon, Connecticut, on April 5, 1767. A twin-brother was graduated a year later, and an older brother a year earlier.
He left College with a high reputation for scholarship and after studying law settled in practice in New London, Connecticut, where he married on March 14, 1790, Lucretia Shaw, the only surviving daughter of the Rev. Ephraim Woodbridge (Yale 1765).
He was one of the Representatives of the city in the General Assembly during eight sessions between 1795 and 1800, and again in 1814 and 1815,--in which last session, as in one in 1798, he served as Speaker of the House.
At a comparatively early date (1799) he was appointed an Assistant Judge of the County, and in 1907 was promoted to the rank of Chief Judge, which he retained until 1825.
In politics he was a Federalist, and as such was elected to Congress for one term, 1801 to 1803. Later he was in the State Senate for six years, from 1817 to 1822, being also for this period ex-officio a Fellow of the Yale Corporation.
From 1829 to 1832 he was Mayor of New London.
He was the first President of the New London Bank, which was chartered in 1907.
In 1817 he was chosen to be a Deacon in the First Congregational Church in New London. An engraving from his full-length portrait is given in a volume of the American National Register.
His wife died on March 6, 1802, in her 29th year; and he next married on February 11, 1805, Mary, second daughter of John and Lucretia (Christophers) Mumford, of the present township of Salem, Connecticut, who died on March 22, 1830, in her 56th year.
By his first wife he had four sons and two daughters. The first and second sons were both graduated at Yale in 1812, and the others died in infancy. The younger daughter married Charles Griswold (Yale 1808).
Mr. Perkins died in New London on September 27, 1845, in his 79th year.
Two of his private letters to Governor Griswold (1800-01) are printed in the Family-Histories and Genealogies of Mr. And Mrs. Salisbury.
(Taken from Biographical Sketches of Yale Colleg e, F. B. Dexter, pp. 502-503).
Students; Lawyers; Politicians; Perkins, Elias, 1767-1845; Perkins, N. S. (Nathaniel Shaw), 1792-1870; Shaw, Nathaniel, 1735-1782; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1786; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1812; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory
  - Elias Perkins, 1767-1845
    - Oration: "A Dispute", 1784 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Oration, untitled, delivered at commencement, 1786 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Yale B.A. diploma, signed by Ezra Stiles and others, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - ALS: notice of election as Phi Beta Kappa orator, signed by Sam Austin, 1789 July 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - ALS relating to election to the 7th Congress of the U.S., signed by Gov. Jonathan Trumbull, 1800 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Certificate of appointment as judge of New London County Court, signed by Gov. Jonathan Trumbull, 1808 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - ALS: concerning the Connecticut Agricultural Society, from John Humphreys for himself and Eli Whitney, 1819 April 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Certificate of appointment as judge of New London County Court, signed by Oliver Wolcott, 1820 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Vote of thanks of the Yale Faculty, signed by Jeremiah Day, 1920 September 8 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - ALS: notice of appointment to the committee to attend the public examination at Yale, signed by Jeremiah Day, 1821 August 16 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Certificate of appointment as judge of New London County Court, signed by Oliver Wolcott, 1822 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Vote of thanks from Yale College treasurer, Wyllys Warner, 1833 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "The Freshman Laws", undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Nathaniel Shaw Perkins, 1797-1870
    - Yale tuition receipt, signed by S. Twining, 1808 September 8 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Yale B.A. diploma, signed by Timothy Dwight, 1812 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Appointment as surgeon's mate in Lt. Col. William Moore's 3rd Regiment, Waterford, signed by William Moore, 1813 July 16 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Yale M.A. diploma, signed by Timothy Dwight, 1813 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Receipts and certificates of admission to classes at the University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine, 1814-1815 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Appointment as surgeon in Lt. Col. Nathan Frank's 2nd Regiment, Horse Artillery, New London, signed by Nathan Frank, 1816 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Certificate of appointment as royal arch mason, New London, signed by Ebenezer Perkins and others, 1818 February (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Nathaniel Shaw Perkins, 1822-1905: letter from the U.S. State Department concerning Nathaniel Shaw, signed by Andrew Allen (Box 1, Folder 21)